Guide to the Carl Geiser Papers ALBA.004
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Carl Geiser Papers
1937-1990, (Bulk 1977-1990)
bulk
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Geiser, Carl
ALBA.004
8 Linear Feet (8 boxes)
Carl Frederick Geiser was born in Orrville, Ohio on December 10, 1910. He fought with the International Brigades in the Spanish Civil War and was taken prisoner and held in a fascist prisoner of war camp for a year before being released in April 1939. After a successful career as an aeronautical engineer, in his retirement he began to research and write a history of American volunteers captured during the Spanish Civil War. His labors resulted in the publication of Prisoners of the Good Fight in 1986. In addition to Geiser’s Spanish Civil War correspondence, this collection consists chiefly of research materials gathered by Geiser in the course of writing his book. It includes correspondence with International Brigade veterans, biographical materials and subject files, along with typescript copies of Geiser’s original 900-page manuscript.
Provenance
The Carl Geiser Papers were donated to Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives by Geiser in 1986. Additional materials were given in 1990. This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Carl Frederick Geiser was born in Orrville, Ohio on December 10, 1910. He was the oldest of six children; his father, a farmer, died in the influenza epidemic at the end of World War I, and his mother a year later of tuberculosis. His maternal grandparents, Swiss immigrants who spoke little English, raised Geiser and his siblings. The young Geiser received his primary education in a one-room schoolhouse while helping to tend the family's sixteen-acre farm. Upon his graduation from Orrville High School in 1928, he enrolled in the YMCA School of Technology (later Fenn College) in Cleveland, where he majored in electrical engineering.
In 1932, following the establishment of diplomatic relations between the United States and the Soviet Union, Geiser was part of the first National Student Federation mission to travel to the newly recognized country. This visit had a decisive influence on shaping Geiser's political thinking. Impressed by the Soviet system and the tenets of socialist ideology, Geiser joined the Young Communist League upon his return to Ohio. He became an active force in the American Student Union in Cleveland and served as a delegate to the First Student Congress Against War and Fascism held in Chicago. It was there that Geiser met his future wife Sylvia, a teacher and organizer who shared his political fervor. The couple moved to New York where they were absorbed into a dynamic culture of political activism and organizing. Geiser wrote press releases and edited International Labor Defense bulletins, organized for the League against War and Fascism, and in 1936 was elected to the National Committee of the Young Communist League.
On April 13, 1937 Geiser boarded the S.S. Georgic to join the International Brigades massing in defense of the Spanish Republic. He served as an ammunition carrier at the Battle of Brunete, saw action at Quinto, and advanced to the rank of Lieutenant. Following the Battle of Belchite in September 1937, Geiser was promoted to Political Commissar and charged with the organization of a training school for commissars at Tarazona. Wounded at the conflict at Fuentes de Ebro, Geiser was hospitalized for three months. Returned to the front as Commissar of the Mackenzie-Papineau Battalion in January 1938, he was captured by fascist forces on April 1, 1938. For the next year, he was interned at San Pedro de Cardeña, along with over 650 International Brigades prisoners. Through the efforts of the Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade and the U.S. State Department, Geiser and a group of 71 Americans were released in April 1939.
Geiser returned to New York and secured an engineering position with Liquidometer, a manufacturer of aeronautic equipment. Working with the company in various capacities for the next 40 years, Geiser filed numerous patents and, as a research director, supervised the testing of a component used in the first lunar mission. He also served briefly as president of Local 1227 of the United Electrical Radio and Machine Workers of America. He and Sylvia had two boys, Jim and Pete, before divorcing in 1946. With his second wife Doris he had a son and a daughter, David and Linda. In 1956 Geiser enrolled at Columbia University's School of General Studies as a psychology major, and graduated with a B.S. degree cum laude in 1963.
By the early 1970s, Geiser turned his attention once more to Spain. At the promptings of his wife, Geiser enrolled in a memoir-writing class. The essay he wrote on a Christmas concert held in San Pedro de Cardeña found publication in The New York Times, and its positive reception provided the impetus for Geiser to produce a more extensive treatment of his concentration camp experience. Upon retirement at age 71, Geiser began to write a comprehensive history of American volunteers captured during the Spanish Civil War. With the assistance of fellow prisoner Robert Steck, Geiser amassed biographical information on the 120 Americans incarcerated in Spanish prisons. He also corresponded with over 150 veterans worldwide to solicit their reminiscences, and traveled to archives in the United States and Europe to conduct research. Ring Lardner, Jr., (whose brother James was killed in action while fighting with the International Brigades) and members of Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, eager to see the project to fruition, provided financial support. Five years of research and writing culminated in the production of a 900-page manuscript. Prisoners of the Good Fight, a shortened version of his account, was published in 1986.
Scope and Content Note
Series I: Correspondence: Spanish Civil War, 1937-1938.
This series consists chiefly of letters written by Geiser to his wife Sylvia (fondly referred to as Impy) and his brother Bennet, and cover the period from his voyage to Europe in April 1937 until shortly before his capture in April 1938. In his letters Geiser describes battalion structure and military training and provides information on his fellow volunteers -- many of them activist colleagues from New York. He also reports on preparations for combat and offers accounts of the battles of Brunete, Quinto, and Belchite, as well as the aftermath of these conflicts. Of note are Geiser's letters to Bennet, in which he defends his reasons for fighting in Spain (5/9/1937 and 6/27/1937), and a letter printed on a leaflet distributed by the International Brigades about the training of officers and political commissars (2/14/1938). This letter also contains a venereal disease prevention leaflet. Other correspondence in this series includes a letter to Sylvia from Paul Wendorf, who with Geiser organized a school for political commissars. Wendorf was killed late in August 1938.
Series II: Correspondence: Prisoners of the Good Fight, 1961; 1970-1990.
This series chiefly includes Geiser's incoming and outgoing correspondence to Abraham Lincoln Brigade and International Brigades veterans produced in the course of conducting research for Prisoners of the Good Fight. Many of these letters offer wartime recollections, research leads, and corrections or corroboration of Geiser's drafted chapters. Notable correspondents include: Ben Iceland, Martin Maki, Herman Lopez, Max Parker, Max Shufer, Mischa Skorupinski, and Hy Wallach. Robert Steck's frequent letters and reports evidence his enormous commitment and extensive contribution to the project. Useful information on Geiser's research can be found in his correspondence with Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives archivist Victor Berch. This series also includes Geiser's exchanges with representatives from his publisher Lawrence Hill & Company and some general correspondence.
Series III: Biographical Files, 1936-1939; 1978-1988.
This series includes biographical sketches of the captured Americans. Carefully researched and written by Geiser and Steck, these biographies are a useful source of information on the wartime experiences of the prisoners and their lives before and after Spain. This series also includes notes, clippings and other materials used in the drafting of these profiles. Consisting chiefly of material on American volunteers, these files also include notes on British, Canandian and other International Brigades volunteers. Although Geiser intended to include these profiles as an appendix to the book, they were omitted from the final published work.
Series IV: Prisoners of the Good Fight: Drafts and Manuscripts, Undated; 1979-1980.
This series contains two typescript versions of Geiser's original 900-page manuscript, an incomplete draft, and chapter notes with corrections and comments by fellow prisoners.
Series V: Subject Files, Undated; 1936-1950; 1973-1990.
This series consists of background files of primary and secondary materials collected and used by Geiser in the course of his research. Included are over two dozen files on prisoners of different nationalities, information on prison conditions and the treatment of inmates, notes and documents related to Red Cross assistance, and materials pertaining to release and repatriation of prisoners. Two articles written by Geiser for the Young Communist, one of them titled "I Was In a Fascist Concentration Camp," can also be found here. Notes taken at various repositories, as well as research photocopies are also located in this series, as are promotional materials related to the publication of Prisoners of the Good Fight.
Arrangement
Series I and II are arranged alphabetically. In series III, six files of general biographical material have been place at the beginning of the series; thereafter, biographical files are arranged alphabetically by personal name. Series IV and V are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into 5 series:
Missing Title
I. Correspondence: Spanish Civil War.
II. Correspondence: Prisoners of the Good Fight.
III. Biographical Files.
IV. Prisoners of the Good Fight: Drafts and Manuscripts.
V. Subject Files.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Paul Wendorf Papers, ALBA #120
Robert Steck Papers, ALBA #104
Separated Material
Photographs from the Carl Geiser Collection have been transferred to the non-print section of the ALBA collection in the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives.
Belchite (Spain) -- History -- Siege, 1937.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives.; Soldiers |z Spain |v Biography.; Soldiers |z United States |v Biography.; Prisoners of war |z Spain |v Biography.; Prisoners of war |z United States |v Biography.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Prisoners and prisons.; Research (document genres).; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Atrocities.; Ebro River, Battle of the, Spain, 1938.; Biography files.; Articles.; Correspondence.; Personal papers.; Brunete, Battle of, Brunete, Spain, 1937.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Campaigns.; Drafts (documents); International Red Cross and Red Crescent Movement; Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives; Wallach, Hy; Skorupinski, Mischa.; Shufer, Max.; Parker, Max, 1912-1983.; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Brigada Internacional, XV--Biography; Lopez, Herman.; Maki, Martin.; Berch, Victor A.; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Steck, Robert; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV; Geiser, Carl; Iceland, Benjamin, 1910-1990; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion
- Series I: Correspondence: Spanish Civil War
  - Geiser, Carl: Outgoing Correspondence, Apr 1937-May 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Geiser, Carl: Outgoing Correspondence, Jun 1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Geiser, Carl: Outgoing Correspondence, Jul 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Geiser, Carl: Outgoing Correspondence, Aug 1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Geiser, Carl: Outgoing Correspondence, Sep 1937 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Geiser, Carl: Outgoing Correspondence, Oct 1937 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Geiser, Carl: Outgoing Correspondence, Nov 1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Geiser, Carl: Outgoing Correspondence, Dec 1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Geiser, Carl: Outgoing Correspondence, Jan 1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Geiser, Carl: Outgoing Correspondence, Feb 1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Geiser, Carl: Outgoing Correspondence, Mar 1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Geiser, Carl: Incoming Correspondence, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Geiser, Sylvia: Incoming Correspondence: Ben Finley, Paul Wendorf, Unidentified, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series II: Correspondence: Prisoners of the Good Fight
  - Acker, Sylvia (George Boehm’s widow), 1983 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Allen, Richard S., 1981-1990 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Alvarez, Manuel, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Amble, Karla, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Amery, Al, 1978-1989 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Anderson, Melvin, 1983-1990 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Argirakis, Matthew, 1978-1986 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Asa, Albert, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Barr, Reuben, 1979-1990 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Bauman, Gerald (Gino), 1979-1989 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Beeching, Bill, 1981-1988 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Benét, Jim, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Berch, Victor, 1977-1988 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Bessie, Alvah, 1979-1985 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Bjoze, Jack, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Black, Margaret, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Blackman, Frank, 1970-1989 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Blair, John C., 1977-1982 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Bortz, Louis, 1978-1988 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Brandt, Joseph, 1961, 1982-1988 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Bridenthal, Kenneth, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Bron, Michal, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Burke, Lee (Canadian), 1977-1990 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Burns, Paul, 1979-1985 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Cameron, James, 1978-1985 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Cesarini, Juan Carlos, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Chase, Homer B., 1978-1985 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Chase, Van Rensalaer, 1978-1985 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Christiansen, Marius (Danish), 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Cloyes, Shirley (Lawrence Hill & Co. Publishers), 1986-1990 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Cogswell, Theodore, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Cohen, Florence and Herman, 1982-1987 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Colodny, Robert, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Colow, Maury, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Cronin, Sean, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - David, Clayton C., 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Davidson, Donald, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Dent, Wally (Canada), 1978-1988 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Dommauer, Olaf and Ann, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Doménech, Jesús, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Dunbar, John, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Edelstein, Florence, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Edwards, Lionel, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Entwistle, Tom, 1981-1990 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Epstein, David, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Ersler, Gabriel, 1982-1988 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Eschweger, John, undated, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Eshag, Eprime, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Esteban, Efren, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Fasanella, Ralph, 1985-1988 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Felsen, Milton, 1981-1989 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Fernandez Lopez, Jose-Angel, 1987-1990 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Firmin, John (Canadian), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Fishman, Moe, 1979-1988 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Friedberg, Saul, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Furr, Grover C., 1987 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Gate, John, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Geist, Anthony, 1981-1987 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, undated, 1978-1983 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, 1984-1990 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Gerassi, John, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Giler, Henry, 1976-1987 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Gittleson, Lester, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Goff, Irving, 1979-1988 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Goldin, Frances, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Goldin, Frances, 1984-1990 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Goldring, Ben, 1978-1987 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Goldstein, Ben, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Goldstein, Dave and Janette, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Gonshak, Sam, 1979-1985 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Graeber, Kenneth, 1978-1981 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Groden, Dan, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Grunblatt, Jacques and Hilda, 1984-1989 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Hafner, Otto and Lola, 1985-1990 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Hall, Charles, 1977-1988 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Harriman, Manny, 1977, 1986-1989 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Harris, Sidney, 1978-1989 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Heinricher, Stanley, 1978-1989 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Henke, Georg, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Hesketh, Harry, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Hill, Lawrence (Lawrence Hill & Co. Publishers), 1983-1988 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Hodge, Edward, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Hutchins, Evelyn, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Iceland, Ben, 1980-1989 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Johnson, John (Canadian), 1978 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Kormes, Karl, 1980-1990 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Kowalski, Artur, 1982-1987 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Kraxner, Joseph, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Lamb, Constance, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Landis, Art, 1978-1985 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Lardner, Ring, Jr., 1980-1988 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Lehman, George, 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Lending, Ed, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Lerner, Sol, 1978-1985 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Levander, Kurt (Swedish), 1988 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Levenson, Leonard, 1983-1988 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Levine, Allan, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Levitas, Maurice (English), 1983-1990 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Lindbak, Ellen, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Locksmith, Nathan, 1979-1988 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Lopez, Herman, 1978-1988 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Lorson, James, 1975-1985 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Love, Vaughn, 1978-1989 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Maki, Martin, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Martin, Fredericka, 1978-1987 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Matthews, Bill (Canadian), 1980-1988 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - McCarthy, William, 1982-1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - McKenna, James B. (SUNY at Stonybrook), 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - McLaughlin, Barry, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Miller, William Colfax, 1980-1988 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Merriman Wachtel, Marion, 1978-1987 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Moon, Jimmy (English), undated, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Moser, Clarence, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Murra, John, 1978-1981 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Nelson, Steve, 1981-1986 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Norris, Len (Canadian), 1978-1987 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Nusser, Charles, 1983-1989 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - O’Reilly, Gerald, 1981-1987 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - O’Riordan, Manus, 1987-1990 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Ochshorn, Maurice, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Okun, Robert, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Ornitz, Lou, 1978-1983 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Ortas, Francisco Martinez (Spanish), 1986-1990 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Paivio, Jules, 1978-1988 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Panagakis, Peter, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Parker, Max and Mary, 1978-1988 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Patton, Ralph (Air Forces Escape & Evasion Society), 1989 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Peet, Dimiter (Bulgarian), 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Perna, Michael, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Persoff, Jim, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Poling, Eugene, 1939, 1983-1990 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Prago, Al, 1979-1987 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Proctor, Raymond, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Radulovic, Savo, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Rappaport, Irving, 1981-1986 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Reed, Bob, 1978-1989 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Riffe, Carl, 1983-1987 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Robinson, John, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Rosenstein, Herman, 1979-1985 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Ross, Adolph, 1983-1988 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Rubens, Bill and Irene, 1978-1989 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Salzman, Salman, 1987-1989 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Schuetrum, Walter J., 1977-1987 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Schütt, Willi, 1981-1986 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Sennet, William, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Service, Elman, 1980-1985 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Shapiro, Linn, 1979-1984 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Sheilds, Art, 1979-1985 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Shufer, Max and Jane, 1978-1990 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Sills, Samuel Jay, 1980-1987 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Sinobas del Almo, Humberto, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Skorupinski, Mischa, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Skup, Paul, 1978-1989 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Smith, Dave and Sophie, 1981-1985 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Smith, Randall B. (Pete), 1976-1988 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Sorkin, Rose, 1981-1987 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Stamm, Morris, 1976-1987 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Stanley, Fred, 1979-1989 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Steck, Robert, undated, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Steck, Robert, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Steck, Robert, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Steck, Robert, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Steck, Robert, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Stevens, Barbro Forslund, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Sugrue, Dan, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Susman, William, 1979-1987 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Tabb, William, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Tabb, Herbert (Hy), 1981-1987 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Tenor, Leon and Patrick, 1978-1987 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Thornton, Ralph, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Tisa, John, 1979-1985 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Tivin, Isadore, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Tormey, Jim, 1939, 1981-1987 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Totis, Luigi and Zoia, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Vance, Cyrus, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Villar Estaban, Fausto, 1986-1989 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Wallach, Hy, 1978-1985 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Warren, Ann, 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Watson, William, 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Watt, George, 1980-1988 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Weissman, Irving, 1982-1987 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Wellman, Paul, 1978-1989 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Wolff, Milton, 1980-1990 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Wyden, Peter, 1981-1987 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Young, Joseph, 1978-1985 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Series III: Biographical Files
  - Biographical Materials: General, undated, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Biographical Materials: Abello-Gustafson, undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Biographical Materials: Haber-Muscala, undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Biographical Materials: Neafus-Niegler, undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Biographies of Captured American Volunteers: A-Z (draft), undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Biographies of Captured American Volunteers: A-Z (incomplete, annotated), undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Abarca Moreno, Manuel, undated (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Abello, Thomas, undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Acken, Edgar, undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Aiking, Chang, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Alexander, Bill, undated (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Anderson, Ray, undated (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Andreasen, Alf (Al), undated (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Argirakis, Matthew, undated (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Arnold, Jack, undated (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Basky, Sidney, undated, 1983-1985 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Balagurchik, Ilya, undated (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Barr, Charles, undated (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Bauman, Gerald (Gino), undated (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Bay, Charles A., undated (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Belau, Carl, undated (Box 4, Folder 43)